let's move now to segmentation
so we have this process A in memory
this is from the previous example
and we know that if we look inside what is
the content of
A in memory we have different parts in the
process this we
discussed in the very beginning
we have stack, heap, data and text
so what if instead of talking of a process
as a single monolithic
block that goes from zero to max we actually
start distinguishing
different parts for the process
this could be motivated by the fact that we
know that the
different parts of the process have different
purposes
there is one keeps only text that is basic
instructions that
are run by the process and taken by the CPU
there are global variables and other parts
so each part
has its own meaning and some might need protection
that
is different from the protection needed by others
and they can also have different sizes
some of them might be fixed
some of them might be actually variable
so there is a reason to differentiate between
the different
parts well with segmentation
the idea is that instead of keeping a single pair
of where the
process starts and what is the limit
we keep a lot of or a certain number of these
pairs one for
each segment
and a segment is just one portion of the process
which could
be one of the different parts
so we can say that we have four segments one
for the text
one for the data one for the heap and one for
the stack
they are numbered 0 to 3
now for each such segment we have the first
physical address
and the limit
it allows you to check with finer grained
resolution
what is happening
because now it's not just checking whether
you are addressing
the member of the process but also checking
whether we
are trying to enter into let's say the data
section or
the heap or the stack and so on
you can even have different permissions for
the different
segments for example you can put the permission
to execute
only to the text section because that is where
you keep
the instructions
and you could for example say that cannot
be written but
can only be read for example
so you can protect a bit better the process
because no one
can try to tamper the instructions and change
the code that
you're trying to run
and of course the nice thing here is that
now you can have
the different segments at different positions
in memory
you don't need to have a contiguous set of
addresses to contain
the entire process
so this is how it looks like you need to introduce
in this
case a table in which you keep track of all
the different
starting addresses and limits
so you have one entering the table for each
segment line
zero it's for segment zero
line one is for segment one and so
and for each segment you have the limit and
the base
okay this is just a picture showing that one
process has
seven segments in this case and they are distributed
around
the memory
this is what we just said that
you need to keep of course track of the different
limit
and based numbers
you also need to complicate a bit the hardware
in this case
because you cannot check as we
did before
if you are trying to other access a logical
address that
is below the limit
and then if that is the case just sum the
base register
or the relocation register here
you need to specify what is the segment you
want to access
and then you will need to specify the address
inside that
segment so given the segment you can go to
the segment
table and take the respective entry for
that segment
and then this will give you the limit and
the base address
if you are trying to access something that
is within the
limit of your segment it's fine
then you can just sum here the base and get
access to the physical
memory otherwise there will be an interrupt
so you can wake up the operating system and
the operating
system to take a decision about what to
do with this
process